James Polen

Human Resource Professional

Old Orchard Beach, ME - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/James-Polen/27bea0641496f72a

Human Resources Professional with 15+ years of experience in multiple industries, both profit and nonprofit with single and multi-state locations. Diverse management and generalist experience with small to mid-size organizations with the ability to align human resources with achieving business objectives. Demonstrated experience in:

Talent Acquisition
Employee/Labor Relations
Benefits Administration
Human Resource Administration
Training
Safety
Public Presentation Skills
Sales and Marketing
Authorized to work in the US for any employer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Human Resources Manager

Frontier Environmental Services - Jones Mills, PA - August 2013 to May 2016

Responsibilities

- Provide first time HR leadership, direction and expertise for a rapidly growing, 350 employee company, in the Marcellus Shale industry.
- Develop client relationships with Project Managers, Superintendents, Managers and Employees to include: providing guidance for employee development, workplace instructions and employment law interpretations.
- Utilize Predictive Index (PI) to improve employee selection process and develop strategies to reduce turnover.
- Facilitate conflict resolution and crisis intervention.
- Advise and counsel Managers on performance and corrective actions with employees.
- · Coordinated staffing efforts for each work site.
- Consult with Managers to Implement Process Improvement initiatives.
- Provide a resource to employees to discuss a variety of opportunity areas or concerns on items such as performance, attendance, compensation, disability, benefits, leaves of absence, etc.
- Assist each worksite to include the development and training of Equal Employment, Diversity, Employment Practices, Sexual Harassment Prevention and Employment Law.
- Attend unemployment hearings and conduct investigations and prepare responses.

Human Resource Manager

The Anderson-DuBose Company - Pittsburgh, PA - 2008 to 2012

Developed/executed human resources policies and procedures for a satellite distribution center for the world's largest restaurant chain. Worked with offsite HR team and Management by providing guidance and counseling to align organizational goals, objectives and strategies and insured the consistent and fair application throughout the company.

- Responsible for full cycle talent acquisition for Management, Transportation and laborers by providing guidance and directions to meet compliance and daily metrics. Increased Affirmative Action by 15%
- Administered employee and labor relations by providing guidance and counseling to managers, supervisors and employees to assist them in effective leadership
- Trained Managers and Supervisors on behavioral based interviewing for consistency and to meet compliance issues
- Provided HR level support and consultative services to Managers, Supervisors and Employees in areas such as, but not limited to: recruitment strategy, career direction and corporate policies
- Administered employee benefits programs, FMLA, OSHA and Workers Compensation
- Assisted in weekly payroll (ADP and Paychex)
- Member of the management team and safety committee

INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR / CONSULTANT

INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR/CONSULTANT - 2000 to 2008

Behavioral Based Assessor, Development Dimensions International

• Screened and identified current laborers for large automotive selection project

Consultant/Human Resources Information System, Pittsburgh Baseball Club

- Consulted with HR to identify current HR needs and worked with Finance and IT for transition
- Created HRIS selection matrix and matched needs with internal costs
- Managed the implementation of HRIS

Recruiter/Marketing, Interim Healthcare of Pittsburgh

- Sourced, identified and screened registered nurses for local healthcare facilities. Created first recruiting database to track candidates and interviewing process.
- Marketed to healthcare facilities to obtain new contracts to provide healthcare professionals

Executive Sales Recruiter, FreeMarkets, Inc. (Posti & Assoc.)

• Sourced, identified, screened and recommended national account executive candidates, James R. Polen, 412-973-3591, jrpolen@hotmail.com

Technical Recruiter / Generalist, eflatbed.com

A transportation eMarketplace dedicated to providing logistics services to flatbed motor carriers

- Developed recruiting strategies for technical and management-level positions such as project manager, HTML and Java developers, XML, quality assurance, technical writers, business development managers
- Consulted with Director, Employee Development in various human resource areas, including change management, recruiter and employee relations

Managing Director, Pittsburgh Office

ProResource, Inc., Cleveland, OH - 1996 to 1999

Provider of interim/contract professionals, executives and consultants

- Developed Interim management assignments and the qualification of appropriate candidates for position openings
- Educated companies and executives on the value of utilizing alternative staffing as a cost effective and viable tool
- Identified, recruited, screened, and presented potential candidates for clients' open positions
- Started the office with one account and managed the office to its first profitable month by the sixth month; doubled the revenue of the Pittsburgh office each year to over \$1 million total dollars.

EDUCATION

Computer Networking Curriculum

Community College of Allegheny County

BSBA in Business Administration, Human Resources

West Virginia University - Morgantown, WV

LINKS

http://linkedin.com/in/jamesrpolen

CERTIFICATIONS/LICENSES

Predictive Index Analyst

August 2014 to Present

GROUPS

Society for Human Resource Mangement

December 2013 to Present

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

COMPUTER SKILLS LEVEL

Advanced in Word, Excel, Access, Explorer, Outlook, ADP and Paychex Payroll Intermediate in PowerPoint and web-based products